# Fatih Sayin

# **Data Analyst**

Austin, TX 78729 fmsayin@hotmail.com (512) 765 3221

I am a strategic and multidisciplinary data analyst and professor in research methodology and theory with 10 years of experience in colleges. I worked as a school principal, university department chair and secretary general for 7 years earlier in my career. I combined my 17 years of expertise in research methodology, project management, and administrative experience with creative data analytics methods and gathered the best results.

Major skills and expertise: Has an eye for innovation and analytical perfection. Collects, cleans, analyzes, visualizes, stores, and makes meaningful highlights out of the data with the best tools available. Proactively perfects skill sets and deepens experience with the tools VBA, Python, SQL, HTML, CSS, MongoDB, JavaScript, D3.js, Tableau, and Hadoop.

- Used fuzzy logic approach for hypothesis testing to validate data and interpretations
- Proposed solutions to improve system efficiencies and reduce total expenses
- Presented data and analysis in order to improve strategies and operations in academic institutions
- Performed data-driven cultural research to highlight nuances between the general and target business
- Detail-oriented, thorough, initiative, solution-seeker, enthusiastic-friendly team member, and excellent in understanding collaborative project-management to achieve high demands.

Authorized to work in the US for any employer

# Work Experience

### **Investment Consultant and Data Analyst**

Cosmos Trading Inc - Austin, TX January 2019 to Present

Investment Consultant and Data Analyst

### **Data Analytics and Visualization**

The University of Texas at Austin - Austin, TX October 2018 to Present

# **Freelance Researcher**

The University of Texas at Austin / Huston-Tillotson University - Austin, TX August 2016 to September 2018

As a freelance researcher, to improve my English skills and research experience:

• I followed some courses at Huston-Tillotson University in Austin, Texas: International Relations and Urban Politics under the supervision of Dr. Robert M. Ceresa and Comparative Religion under the supervision of Dr. James Kraft.

- I followed the course named U.S. Military Interventions under the supervision of Professor Jason Brownlee at the University of Texas at Austin.
- I carried on research to reach data to publish a scientific article (Political Relations between Turkey and Georgia in the Post-Soviet Era. Journal of Liberty and International Affairs)

# **Founding Director of The Alliance of Civilizations Research Center**

Canik Basari University - Samsun, Turkey September 2014 to July 2016

I had the responsibilities of;

- providing leadership toward the achievement of the highest possible level of excellence in the research and service activities of the center.
- managing researcher and student, data and processes
- providing research center requests both within and out of the center in pursuit of its aims and maintaining a climate that is hospitable and encouraging university engagement, participation, collegiality, and innovation.
- developing the center research programs within the mission of the university.
- guiding the research center strategic planning process.
- creating a dynamic and forward looking research environment for both staff and students Moreover, I worked as the Founding Director of the Alliance of Civilizations Center for Research and Applications at Canik Basari University. I organized several national and international conferences and seminars about intercultural dialogue. I collaborated with some Russian and Malaysian academics for these conferences.

# **Adviser to the University President**

Canik Basari University - Samsun, Turkey September 2012 to July 2016

- Analyzed academic evaluations to report to the university board and set reasonable, achievable academic goals.
- Worked on the investment strategies and recommendations, and provided objective advice to the university board to make the correct decisions.
- Wrote academic research summaries and made informed recommendations.
- Directed in consultation with the university president, and planned academic achievement.
- Oversaw the administration of confidential evaluations of the president for Academic Affairs.

### **Department Chair of International Trade and Business Administration**

Canik Basari University - Samsun, Turkey September 2012 to July 2016

As the department chair, my primary role was to provide strong academic and administrative leadership. For this reason, I led, managed and developed the department to ensure it achieved the highest possible standards of excellence in all its activities, and empowered others in order to deliver the agreed departmental strategy within the faculty. Active member of the Faculty Executive Board and contribute to the overall leadership and management of the department. With the same purpose, I was responsible for:

- setting and advancing the academic strategy of the department in line with faculty and university strategic plans and direction.
- implementing university policy and rules within the department.
- managing student data and processes
- refreshing and developing new programs in order to attract new students and markets

- preparing and proposing department budget requests.
- carrying out to the highest possible standards and put in place the necessary evaluation and monitoring procedures to ensure both compliance and improvement: such procedures will include teaching, research and management of all resources

### **Assistant Professor**

Canik Basari University - Samsun, Turkey September 2012 to July 2016

- Delivered some classes to students which were International Organizations, Research Methodology and Theory.
- Fulfilled the responsibilities concerning students in respect of their admission, instruction, progress and examination.
- Ensured the highest levels of quality, integrity and ethics in all research undertaken
- Created and exploited new opportunities for knowledge transfer activity in order to secure additional income streams and new areas of teaching and/or research

#### **Assistant Professor**

International Black Sea University - Tbilisi, Georgia September 2009 to July 2011

- Delivered some classes to students which were International Organizations, Research Methodology and Theory.
- Fulfilled the responsibilities concerning students in respect of their admission, instruction, progress and examination.
- Ensured the highest levels of quality, integrity and ethics in all research undertaken
- Created and exploited new opportunities for knowledge transfer activity in order to secure additional income streams and new areas of teaching and/or research

### **Secretary General**

International Black Sea University - Tbilisi, Georgia June 2009 to July 2011

- Established and implemented short and long term organizational goals, objectives, strategic plans, policies, and operating procedures; monitored and evaluated programmatic and operational effectiveness, and effects on changes required for improvement.
- Developed and administered annual budgets for the unit and programs, performed periodic cost analysis and produced customized expense reports.
- Managed student and staff, data and processes
- Supported students and staff in the analysis and use of data to drive instruction.
- Ensured all staff access to the necessary support to enable them to contribute fully and develop their skills and experience.

#### Related department:

- Directorate of Administrative & Financial Affairs
- Directorate of Computing (Computer Center)
- Directorate of Strategy Development
- Directorate of Student Affairs (Registrar's Office)
- Directorate of Construction & Technical Works
- Directorate of Health, Culture & Sports
- Directorate of Library & Documentation (Library)
- Directorate of Personnel Affairs

# **Department Chair of Social Activities**

International Black Sea University - Tbilisi, Georgia July 2007 to August 2009

I worked with professors, parents, and school administrators to develop plans and strategies to improve students' academic performance and social development. There were two different departments under my supervision which were Career Department, and Social, Cultural and Sport department. I was in charge of;

- providing support to those who applied for scholarship.
- assessing students' needs, situations, strengths, and supporting with networks to determine their goals
- developing plans to improve students' well-being
- organizing training, supervision, and meetings.
- managing student data and processes

As a social workers I also helped other people:

• I welcomed the refugees of Southern Ossetia during the Georgian-Russian conflict in 2008 at the International Black Sea University (IBSU), where I worked as the secretary general. I took part in serving food and shelter to 400 refugees for 45 days under the support of IBSU. After the refugees left the shelter, we continued to financially support 100 of them for another year until they completed their social integration.

# **Founding Principal**

Nikoloz Tsereteli International School - Tbilisi, Georgia July 2006 to June 2007

- Collaborated with the executive director in planning, hiring, and executing the opening of the secondary school for the 2004-2005 school years and elementary school for the 2006-2007 school years.
- Managed student and staff, data and processes
- · Managed income and expenditure in order to promote financial sustainability
- Managed disciplinary issues of students and worked collaboratively with Shaped the vision of academic success for all students and stuff
- Created a climate to hospitable education
- Cultivated leadership in others
- Managed research and analyzed policy concepts, complex policy issues, and legal implications of proposed school business policies through publications, state, and local laws, regulations, guidelines, and other institutions.

## **Founding Principal**

Niko Nikoladze Secondary School - Kutaisi, Georgia July 2004 to June 2006

- Collaborated with the executive director in planning, hiring, and executing the opening of the secondary school for the 2004-2005 school years and elementary school for the 2006-2007 school years.
- Managed student and staff, data and processes
- Managed income and expenditure in order to promote financial sustainability
- Managed disciplinary issues of students and worked collaboratively with Shaped the vision of academic success for all students and stuff
- Created a climate to hospitable education
- Cultivated leadership in others

• Managed research and analyzed policy concepts, complex policy issues, and legal implications of proposed school business policies through publications, state, and local laws, regulations, guidelines, and other institutions.

# Education

# **Data Analytics and Visualization**

The University of Texas at Austin - Austin, TX October 2018 to 2019

### **Doctorate in International Relations**

Ivane Javakhishvili State University - Tbilisi, Georgia September 2003 to June 2009

### **Bachelor's in International Relations**

Free University of Tbilisi - Georgia September 1995 to June 2000

### Skills

• Data Analysis, • Python Programming: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, API Interactions, • Fundamental Statistics: Modeling, Forecasting, • Databases: SQL, SqlAlchemy, MongoDB, SQLite, • Web Visualization: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Dashboarding, JavaScript, • Business Analysis, • Advanced Excel Functions: Pivot Tables, VBA Scripting

# Links

https://fmsayin.github.io

https://github.com/fmsayin

https://www.linkedin.com/in/fatih-sayin